[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter records, Inclusive: 1897-2006, undated, Bulk: 1960-1990
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter records
Inclusive: 1897-2006, undated, Bulk: 1960-1990
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2108
Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter, 1901 -
31 document boxes and 7 oversized boxes.
[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter records contain materials from the organization’s activities in the McLennan County area from 1901 to the mid-2000s. These include correspondence, minutes, scrapbooks, historical essays, yearbooks, programs, clippings, handbooks, and directories.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The 1890s were a time of heightened patriotism, with many all-male fraternities celebrating an
individual’s ancestors who had fought in the American Revolution. Women were often excluded from this opportunity to celebrate one’s lineage and patriotism. On 1890 October 11, a group of women banded together in Washington, D.C. to counter such exclusion. They formed the National Society, Daughters of the American Revolution (NSDAR). The NSDAR had a three-fold mission of educating the public, historic preservation, and open displays of patriotism. Since its inception, the NSDAR has welcomed over 800,000 members into its ranks.
The popularity of the NSDAR quickly spread across the nation. On 1901 December 5, Mrs. Josie Downs Marshall and fourteen other charter members from McLennan County founded the Henry Downs Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution. Henry Downs was famous for having signed the Mecklenburg Declaration (1775). This declaration has stirred heated controversy in scholarly circles. Its signers from Charlotte, North Carolina, claimed that it was the first declaration of independence crafted in the original thirteen colonies.
Downs was born near Spotsylvania County, Virginia, in 1728. Upon marrying his wife Frames Chew at the age of 22, Downs moved to North Carolina where he gained military experience fighting local Cherokee Indians during the final stages of the French and Indian War. What garnered the most fame for Henry Downs was the act of signing the Mecklenburg Declaration (1775).
Officers in the Henry Downs Chapter were quite particular concerning those whom they granted
membership. Applicants had to be women of eighteen years of age or older who could trace their lineage to aRevolutionary War ancestor. In addition to these genealogical requirements, potential inductees had to exhibit strong moral character as well. The group, in addition to focusing on the three-fold mission of the national organization, was very involved within the local community.
For much of the twentieth century, the Henry Downs Chapter enjoyed relative success and growth at achieving this goal. One of the first ways in which the chapter impacted local community life in Waco was the creation of historical markers. Since 1917, the Henry Downs Chapter has placed historical markers at Waco Springs, the home site of Governor Richard Coke, the home of Neill McLennan, Fort House, and First Street Cemetery.
The chapter also celebrates American military and civic life. It awards annual medals to cadets and troops in the ROTC program at Baylor University. The D.A.R. has also overseen numerous middles school historical essay contests, as attested by the large number of student essays found within the collection. While celebrating their American heritage, the D.A.R. also reaches out to immigrant populations by encouraging them to take citizenship classes at nearby naturalization courts.
In 1976, as part of a bicentennial project conducted by the chapter, Sara Evans and Urena Johnson
sought to create a new chapter of the D.A.R. One of the primary reasons for this course of action was the difficulty young mothers had in attending the meetings of the Henry Downs Chapter, which
to date had always been held in the afternoon or evenings. Evans and Johnson were able to recruit the thirty-six members necessary in order to start a new chapter. On 1976 October 15, these women met in an organizational meeting with the purpose of forging a new group: the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter. The Texas Collection houses the collections of both D.A.R. chapters.
Scope and Content
The chronology of the [Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter records ranges from the inception of the Henry Downs Chapter in 1901 to the most recent donation given in 2002. Materials represent a wide variety including personal/institutional correspondence, minutes, membership applications, financial documents, historical essays, artifacts, and scrapbooks. The content of these papers tell the comprehensive history of the Henry Downs Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution. An emphasis is placed on the service activities that the chapter performed in the community as well as the infrastructure of the organization at national, state, and local levels. Researchers interested in genealogy will want to examine the lineages of various members located in the applications series.
Arrangement
The [Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter records, prior to processing, lacked consistent organization. The materials were in good condition, but had been received through approximately twenty donations and were packed tightly in ten storage file boxes. A box inventory and preliminary processing plan led to the creation of eight series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, III. Minutes, IV. Applications, V. Literary Productions, VI. Artifacts, VII. Photographic Materials, and VIII. Scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2108. Acquired 1980-02-27
Related Resources
Items in related collections
[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley records, Inclusive: 1956-2002, undated, Bulk: 1977-2002
Related references
“About DAR.” Daughters of the American Revolution. Accessed 2012 May 16.
“Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter NSDAR.” Daughters of the American Revolution. Accessed 2012 May 16.
“Henry Downs Chapter.” Daughters of the American Revolution. Accessed 2012 June 14.
Johnson, Mrs. Hubert. “Daughters of the American Revolution, Henry Downs Chapter.” The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas. Ed. Dayton Kelley. Waco: Texian Press, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Daughters of the American Revolution.
Subjects
Societies -- Membership -- Texas -- Waco.; United States -- History -- Revolution.
Genres
Brochures.; Certificates.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Handbooks and manuals.; Membership lists.; Minutes (Records); Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Programs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1904-1989; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The following series is comprised of folders containing correspondence exchanged among members and officers of the National Society Daughters of the American Revolution, the Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution, and the Henry Downs Chapter. The packets of correspondence include letters from the national branch explaining the duties of officers, upcoming events, by-laws, and other workings of the organization. This series is in good condition.
  - General, 1904-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1974-1977 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1977 September-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1980-1981 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1981 June-1982 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1982 June-1984 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, 1984 October-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 2), 1966 July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 2), 1966 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 2), 1967 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 2), 1967 June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 3), 1974 July (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 3), 1974 July (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 3), 1974 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 4), 1976 July (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 4), 1976 July (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 4), 1976 July (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 4), 1976 July (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 4), 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 4), 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 4), 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 4), 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 5), 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 5), 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 5), 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 5), 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (5 of 5), 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 4), 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 4), 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 4), 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 4), 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (5 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (6 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (7 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (8 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (9 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (10 of 10), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 4), 1981 June (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 4), 1981 June (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 4), 1981 June (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 4), 1981 June (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (5 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (6 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (7 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (8 of 8), 1982 June (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 6), 1983 July (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 6), 1983 July (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 6), 1983 July (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 6), 1983 July (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (5 of 6), 1983 July (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Packet: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (6 of 6), 1983 July (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Packet: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (1 of 5), 1979 July (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Packet: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (2 of 5), 1979 July (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Packet: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (3 of 5), 1979 July (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Packet: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (4 of 5), 1979 July (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Packet: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution: (5 of 5), 1979 July (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Financial Documents, 1923-1999; 2
  The following series is comprised of financial documents pertaining to the Henry Downs Chapter Finance Committee, budgets, receipts, treasurer’s reports, and pamphlets outlining the official duties of the chapter treasurer. The materials are in good condition.
  - General: Finance Committee, 1923-1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - General: Finance Committee, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - General: Finance Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General: Finance Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General: Finance Committee, 1962-1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General: Finance Committee, 1974-1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Receipts and Disbursements, 1978 June-1983 April (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Financial Documents: Receipts and Disbursements, 1983 May-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reports: Henry Downs Chapter, 1989 November-1990 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Reports: Henry Downs Chapter, 1990 April-December (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Reports: Henry Downs Chapter, 1991 January-July (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Reports: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution, 1978 January 31 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Reports: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution, 1999 January 31 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reports: Treasurer, 1976 October-1978 March (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Minutes, 1930-1991; 3
  The following series is comprised of the monthly minutes recorded by the Henry Downs Chapter. Also included are notes concerning the proceedings of the National Society Daughters of the American Revolution and Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution. These materials shed helpful insights into the inner workings of the D.A.R. on the national, state, and local levels. The materials are in average to good condition.
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1930 June-December (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1931 January-March (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1931 May-October (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1931 November-December (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1932 January-March (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1932 April-October (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1932 November-1933 January (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1933 February-November (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1933 December-1934 March (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1934 April-May (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1934 October-December (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1935 January-March 1 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1935 March 18-June (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1935 July-December (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1936 January-March (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1936 April-June (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1936 October-November (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1936 December-1937 February (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1937 March-May (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1937 August-November (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1937 December-1938 March (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1938 April-June (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1938 October-1939 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1939 May-1940 April (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1940 May-1941 January (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1941 February-May (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1941 October-1942 February (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1942 March-May (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1942 October-1943 March (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1943 April-December (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1944 January-April (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1944 May-December (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1945 January-1946 February (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1946 March-June (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1946 September-1948 June (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1948 September-1949 February (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1949 March-October (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1949 November-1950 October (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1950 November-1951 May (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1951 October-1952 April (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1952 May-September (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1952 November-1953 March (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1953 April-November (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1953 December-1954 March (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1954 April-November (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1954 December-1955 February (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1955 March-June (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1955 October-December (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1956 January-February (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1956 March-April (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1956 May-June (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1956 October-December (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1957 January-March (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1957 April-1958 February (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1958 March-June (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1958 October-1959 March (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1959 April-1960 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1960 February-October (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1960 November-1961 April (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1961 May-1962 March (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1962 April-December (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1936 January-April (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1963 May-1964 February (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1964 March-October (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1964 November-1965 April (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1965 May-1966 February (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1966 March-June (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1966 July-1967 March (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1967 April-December (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1968 January-October (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1968 November-1969 October (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1969 November-1970 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1972-1973 May (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1973 June-1974 May (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1974 October-1975 April (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1975 May-1976 April (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1975-1981 September (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1976 May-December (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1976 August-1977 May (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1977 August-1980 May (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1980 June-November (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1980 December-1981 February (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1981 March-June (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1981 July-1982 January (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1982 February-May (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1981 October-1982 April (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1982 May-August (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1982 September-1983 February (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1983 March-June (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1983 August-December (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1984 January-June (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1984 July-1985 April (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Minutes: General: Henry Downs Chapter, 1985 May-1986 February (Box 5, Folder 13)